Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 36: The Puerperium.
The Fourth Trimester Reproductive Tract Involution Placental Site Involution Urinary Tract Peritoneum And Abdominal Wall Blood And Blood Volume Lactation And Breastfeeding Hospital Care Home Care References The word puerperium is derived from Latin—puer, child + parus, bringing forth.
It defines the time following delivery during which pregnancy-induced maternal anatomical and physiological changes return to the nonpregnant state.
Its duration is inexact but is considered to last between 4 and 6 weeks.
Although much less complex compared with pregnancy, the puerperium has appreciable changes, and maternal morbidity is surprisingly common.
For example, in a survey of 1246 British mothers, 3 percent required hospital readmission within 8 weeks .
Moreover, almost three fourths of women continue to have health problems for up to 18 months .
Of self-reported concerns, pain, breastfeeding, and psychosocial topics are prominent.
Table 36-1 lists data on these from the Pregnancy Risk Assessment Surveillance System—PRAMS—of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC).
Table 36-1.
Concerns Raised by Women in the Puerperium The Fourth Trimester.
Because the weeks following childbirth are a critical period for the woman and her infant, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018a) promulgated the concept of a “fourth trimester.
This concept reinforces the importance of the 12 weeks following birth, and components of this model are outlined in Table 36-2.
Thus, the comprehensive postpartum visit includes a full assessment of physical, social, and psychological well-being.
Table 36-2.
Components of Postpartum Care for the Fourth Trimester An initial visit is recommended at 3 weeks postdelivery and a final summary visit at 12 weeks.
Between this time, visits can be added as needed.
For example, women with chronic hypertension, overt diabetes, cardiovascular disease, and depression may require additional multidisciplinary care during this period.
For all puerpera, a discussion of positive lifestyle changes can be initiated.
This time also affords the opportunity to update immunizations .
At the end of the 12-week fourth trimester, follow-up then transitions into well-woman care, ongoing primary or specialty care, and when necessary, preconceptional counseling .
Reproductive Tract Involution.
# Birth Canal.
Return of the tissues in the birth canal to the nonpregnant state begins soon after delivery.
The vagina and its outlet gradually diminish in size but rarely regain their nulliparous dimensions.
Rugae begin to reappear by the third week but are less prominent than before.
The hymen is represented by several small tags of tissue, which scar to form the myrtiform caruncles.
The vaginal epithelium reflects the hypoestrogenic state, and it does not begin to proliferate until 4 to 6 weeks.
This timing is usually coincidental with resumed ovarian estrogen production.
Lacerations or stretching of the perineum during delivery can lead to vaginal outlet relaxation.
Some damage to the pelvic floor may be inevitable, and parturition predisposes to pelvic organ prolapse .
# Uterus.
The massively augmented uterine blood flow necessary to maintain pregnancy derives from significant hypertrophy and remodeling of pelvic vessels.
After delivery, their caliber gradually diminishes to approximately that of the prepregnant state.
Within the puerperal uterus, larger blood vessels become obliterated by hyaline changes.
They are gradually resorbed and replaced by smaller ones.
Minor vestiges of the larger vessels, however, may persist for years.
During labor and vaginal delivery, the margin of the dilated cervix, which corresponds to the external os, may be lacerated.
The cervical opening contracts slowly, and for a few days immediately after labor, it readily admits two fingers.
By the end of the first week, this opening narrows, the cervix thickens, and the endocervical canal reforms.
The external os does not completely resume its pregravid appearance.
It remains
somewhat wider, and typically, ectocervical depressions at the site of lacerations become permanent.
These changes are characteristic of a parous cervix .
Cervical epithelium also undergoes considerable remodeling.
This actually may be salutary because almost half of women have regression of high-grade dysplasia following delivery (Ahdoot, 1998; Kaneshiro, 2005).
Figure 36-1.
Common appearance of nulliparous (A) and parous (B) cervices.
After delivery, the fundus of the contracted uterus lies slightly below the umbilicus.
It consists mostly of myometrium covered by serosa and internally lined by decidua.
The markedly attenuated lower uterine segment contracts and retracts, but not as forcefully as the uterine corpus.
During the next few weeks, the lower segment is converted from a clearly distinct substructure large enough to accommodate the fetal head to a barely discernible uterine isthmus located between the corpus and internal cervical os.
Immediately postpartum, the anterior and posterior walls, which lie in close apposition, are each 4 to 5 cm thick .
At this time, the uterus weighs approximately 1000 g. Myometrial involution is a truly remarkable feat of destruction or deconstruction that begins as soon as 2 days after delivery .
The total number of myocytes does not decline appreciably—rather, their size decreases markedly.
Weights from removed uteri approximate 500 g by 1 week postpartum, 300 g by 2 weeks, and at 4 weeks, involution is complete and the uterus weighs approximately 100 g .
After each successive delivery, the uterus is usually slightly larger than before the most recent pregnancy.
Sonographic Findings Uterine involution and declining uterine volume is best measured by sonography .
With this, estimates again show uterine size declines of more than half, from 450 to 200 g, in the first 2 weeks.
Sonographically, the uterus and endometrium return to the pregravid size by 8 weeks postpartum.
Complete involution in the multiparous uterus is longer than for the nulliparous organ .
In the event of a cesarean delivery, the residual myometrial thickness over the uterine incision is thicker if a two-layer closure was used .
Figure 36-2.
Pattern of uterine involution through 7 weeks postpartum as estimated by sonography.
In a study of 42 normal puerperas, fluid in the endometrial cavity was noted in 78 percent of women at 2 weeks, 52 percent at 3 weeks, 30 percent at 4 weeks, and 10 percent at 5 weeks .
Belachew and coworkers (2012) used three-dimensional sonography and visualized intracavitary tissue matter in a third on day 1, 95 percent on day 7, 87 percent on day 14, and 28 percent on day 28.
By day 56, the small cavity was empty.
Doppler ultrasound of the uterine artery shows continuously increasing vascular resistance throughout the first 7 weeks postpartum (Sohn, 1988; Wataganara, 2015).
Uterine artery flow impedance does not differ between women undergoing vaginal versus cesarean delivery .
Decidual and Endometrial Regeneration Because separation of the placenta and membranes involves the spongy layer, the decidua basalis is not sloughed.
The in situ decidua varies markedly in thickness, it has an irregular jagged border, and it is infiltrated with blood, especially at the placental site.
Within 2 or 3 days after delivery, the remaining decidua becomes differentiated into two layers.
The superficial layer becomes necrotic and is sloughed in the lochia.
The basal layer adjacent to the myometrium remains intact and is the source of new endometrium.
Decidual vessels are near normal by delivery and endovascular trophoblasts are diminished.
These vessels and the spiral arteries also undergo involution .
Endometrial regeneration is rapid, except at the placental site.
Within a week or so, the free surface becomes covered by epithelium.
Sharman (1953) identified a fully restored endometrium in all biopsy specimens obtained from the 16th day onward.
Histological endometritis is part of the normal reparative process.
Also, microscopic inflammatory changes characteristic of noninfectious acute salpingitis
are seen in almost half of women between 5 and 15 days .
Clinical Aspects Afterpains.
Several clinical findings coincide with uterine involution.
In primiparas, the uterus tends to remain tonically contracted following delivery.
In multiparas, however, it often contracts vigorously at intervals and gives rise to afterpains, which are similar to but milder than labor contractions.
These are more pronounced as parity increases and worsen when the newborn suckles, likely because of oxytocin release .
Usually, afterpains decrease in intensity and become mild by the third day.
We have encountered unusually severe and persistent afterpains in women with postpartum uterine infections .
Lochia.
Early in the puerperium, sloughing of decidual tissue results in a vaginal discharge of variable quantity.
The discharge is termed lochia and contains erythrocytes, shredded decidua, epithelial cells, and bacteria.
For the first few days after delivery, there is blood sufficient to color it red— lochia rubra.
After 3 or 4 days, lochia becomes progressively pale in color —lochia serosa.
After approximately the 10th day, because of an admixture of leukocytes and reduced fluid content, lochia assumes a white or yellowwhite color—lochia alba.
The average duration of lochial discharge ranges from 24 to 36 days .
Because of this expected leukocyte component, saline preparations of lochia for microscopic evaluation in cases of suspected puerperal metritis are typically uninformative.
Placental Site Involution.
Complete extrusion of the placental site takes up to 6 weeks .
Immediately after delivery, the placental site is approximately palmsized.
Within hours of delivery, it normally contains many thrombosed vessels that ultimately undergo organization.
By the end of the second week, it measures 3 to 4 cm in diameter.
Placental site involution is an exfoliation process, which is prompted in great part by undermining of the implantation site by new endometrial proliferation .
Thus, involution is not simply absorption in situ.
Exfoliation consists of both extension and “downgrowth” of endometrium from the margins of the placental site, as well as “upward” development of endometrial tissue from the glands and stroma left deep in the decidua basalis after placental separation.
Anderson and Davis (1968) concluded that placental site exfoliation results from sloughing of infarcted and necrotic superficial tissues followed by a remodeling process.
# Subinvolution.
In some cases, uterine involution is hindered because of incompletely remodeled spiral arteries, retained placental fragments, or infection.
Such subinvolution is accompanied by varied intervals of prolonged lochia and by irregular or excessive uterine bleeding.
During bimanual examination, the uterus is larger and softer than would be expected.
Inadequate conversion of spiral arteries into remodeled uteroplacental arteries can cause subinvolution .
These noninvoluted vessels are filled with thromboses and lack an endothelial lining.
Perivascular trophoblasts are also identified in the vessel walls, which suggests an aberrant interaction between uterine and trophoblast cells.
With bleeding, pelvic sonography may help differentiate subinvolution from retained placenta.
Characteristic findings of retained products include a thickened endometrium or endometrial mass .
Vascularity within this area increases the likelihood of retained products .
Comparatively, subinvolution is characterized by an enlarged uterus with tubular hypoechoic areas in the myometrium.
These tubular structures reflect neovascularization and dilated uterine vessels.
Figure 36-3.
Sonographic appearance of puerperal uterine complications.
A. Retained products of conception.
Tissue vascularity is highlighted here by color Doppler.
B. Retained clot marked by calipers shows mixed echogenicity in a woman with subinvolutional hemorrhage.
Anechoic cystic areas within the fundal myometrium reflect dilated vessels.
For treatment, uterotonics are recommended by many but their efficacy is questionable (Hoyveda, 2001;
American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2017d).
At Parkland hospital, conservative management is undertaken with methylergonovine (Methergine) 0.2 mg orally every 3 to 4 hours for 24 to 48 hours.
For initially brisk bleeding, an intramuscular dose of methylergonovine may be coupled with an infusion of synthetic oxytocin (Pitocin) (20 units in 1 L crystalloid).
For cases with suspected comorbid infection, antimicrobial therapy usually leads to a good response.
Wager and associates (1980) reported that a third of late cases of postpartum metritis are caused by Chlamydia trachomatis.
Empirical therapy with azithromycin or doxycycline usually prompts resolution regardless of bacterial etiology.
At our institution, common oral options taken twice daily for 7 to 10 days include azithromycin, 500 mg; amoxicillin-clavulanate (Augmentin), 875 mg; or doxycycline, 100 mg. # Late Postpartum Hemorrhage.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017d) defines secondary postpartum hemorrhage as bleeding 24 hours to 12 weeks after delivery.
Clinically worrisome uterine hemorrhage develops within 1 to 2 weeks in perhaps 1 percent of women.
Such bleeding most often stems from abnormal involution of the placental site.
It occasionally is caused by retention of a placental fragment or by a uterine artery pseudoaneurysm.
Rarely, retained products may undergo necrosis with fibrin deposition and neovascularization, thus forming a placental polypoid mass.
Severe hemorrhage occurs in only 6 percent of these cases due to rupture of blood vessels .
Sonographically, a discrete hypervascular endometrial mass that may extend into the myometrium is visualized .
As discussed in Chapter 59 (p. 1062), delayed postpartum hemorrhage may also be caused by von Willebrand disease or other inherited coagulopathies .
Figure 36-4.
Sonogram of a polypoid placental mass with color Doppler applied.
The mass is demarcated by the dashed white lines.
Hypervascularity is seen extending from the mass into the myometrium.
In our experiences, few women with delayed hemorrhage are found to have retained placental fragments.
Thus, we and others do not routinely perform curettage .
Another concern is that curettage may worsen bleeding by avulsing part of the implantation site.
Thus, in a stable patient, if sonographic examination shows an empty cavity, then oxytocin, methylergonovine, or a prostaglandin analogue is given.
Suitable dosing is found in Table 13-3 (p. 240).
Antimicrobials are added if uterine infection is suspected.
If large clots are seen in the uterine cavity with sonography, then gentle suction curettage is considered.
Otherwise, curettage is carried out only if appreciable bleeding persists or recurs after medical management.
Urinary Tract.
Normal pregnancy-induced glomerular hyperfiltration persists during the puerperium but returns to prepregnancy baseline by 2 weeks .
Parturition induces a transient rise in excretion of glomerular podocytes .
Dilated ureters and renal pelves return to their prepregnant state by 2 to 8 weeks postpartum.
Because of this dilated collecting system, coupled with residual urine and bacteriuria in a traumatized bladder, symptomatic urinary tract infection remains a concern in the puerperium.
Funnell and colleagues (1954) used cystoscopy immediately postpartum and described varying degrees of submucosal hemorrhage and edema.
Bladder trauma is associated most closely with labor length and thus to some degree accompanies normal vaginal delivery.
Postpartum, the bladder has a greater capacity and a relative insensitivity to intravesical pressure.
Consequently, overdistention, incomplete emptying, and excessive residual urine are frequent (Buchanan, 2014; Mulder, 2014).
Acute urinary retention is more common with epidural or narcotic analgesia .
The management of urinary retention is discussed later (p. 643).
Stress urinary incontinence during the puerperium may occur in 5 percent of women .
Much attention has been given to the potential for subsequent development of urinary incontinence and other
pelvic floor disorders in the years following delivery .
A more detailed discussion is found in Chapter 30 (p. 548).
Peritoneum And Abdominal Wall.
The broad and round ligaments require considerable time to recover from stretching and loosening during pregnancy.
The abdominal wall remains soft and flaccid as a result of ruptured elastic fibers in the skin and prolonged distention by the gravid uterus.
If the abdomen is unusually lax or pendulous, an ordinary girdle is often satisfactory.
An abdominal binder is another temporary measure.
Several weeks are required for these structures to return to normal, and exercise aids recovery.
These may be started anytime following vaginal delivery.
After cesarean delivery, a 6-week interval to allow anterior abdominal wall fascia to heal and abdominal soreness to diminish is reasonable.
Silvery abdominal striae commonly develop as striae gravidarum .
Except for these, the abdominal wall usually resumes its prepregnancy appearance.
When muscles remain atonic, however, the abdominal wall also remains lax.
Marked separation of the rectus abdominis muscles—diastasis recti— may result.
This separation develops from a gradual thinning and widening of the linea alba and is coupled with a general laxity of the ventral abdominal wall muscles.
Importantly, musculofascial continuity and lack of a true hernia sac differentiates this from a ventral hernia .
Blood And Blood Volume.
# Hematological and Coagulation Changes.
Marked leukocytosis and thrombocytosis may occur during and after labor.
The white blood cell count seldom exceeds 25,000/μL, and the rise is predominantly due to granulocytes (Arbib, 2016; Sanci, 2017).
A relative lymphopenia and an absolute eosinopenia is typical.
Normally, during the first few postpartum days, hemoglobin concentration and hematocrit decrease moderately.
If they fall much below prelabor levels, a considerable amount of blood has been lost.
By the end of pregnancy, laboratory values that assess coagulation are altered .
These changes are discussed in Chapter 4 (p. 61) and listed in the Appendix (p. 1228).
Many extend variably in the puerperium.
For example, a markedly higher plasma fibrinogen level is maintained at least through the first week.
This contributes to hypercoagulability .
As one result, the pregnancy-associated risks for deep-vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism persist in the 12 weeks following childbirth .
# Pregnancy-Induced Hypervolemia.
When the amount of blood attained by normal pregnancy hypervolemia is lost as postpartum hemorrhage, the woman almost immediately regains her nonpregnant blood volume .
If less has been lost at delivery, blood volume generally nearly returns to its nonpregnant level by 1 week after delivery.
Cardiac output usually remains elevated for 24 to 48 hours postpartum and declines to nonpregnant values by 10 days .
Heart rate changes follow this pattern, and blood pressure similarly returns to nonpregnant values .
Correspondingly, systemic vascular resistance remains in the lower range characteristic of pregnancy for 2 days postpartum and then begins to steadily rise to normal nonpregnant values .
Despite this, Morris and coworkers (2015) found that reduced arterial stiffness persists following pregnancy.
They suggest a significant favorable effect of pregnancy on maternal cardiovascular remodeling.
This may represent a mechanism by which preeclampsia risk is reduced in subsequent pregnancies.
Figure 36-5.
During the early puerperium, blood pressure normally rises toward nonpregnant values.
MAP = mean arterial pressure.
# Postpartum Diuresis.
Normal pregnancy is associated with appreciable extracellular sodium and water retention, and postpartum diuresis is a physiological reversal of this process.
Chesley and associates (1959) demonstrated an approximate 2 liter decline in sodium space during the first week postpartum.
This corresponds with loss of residual pregnancy hypervolemia.
In preeclampsia, pathological retention of fluid antepartum and then its normal diuresis postpartum may be prodigious .
Postpartum diuresis results in a relatively rapid weight loss of 2 to 3 kg, which is additive to the 5 to 6 kg incurred by delivery and normal blood loss.
Weight loss from pregnancy itself likely peaks by the end of the second week postpartum.
Any residual weight compared with prepregnancy values probably represents fat stores that will persist.
Lactation And Breastfeeding.
# Breast Anatomy and Secretory Products.
Each mature mammary gland or breast is composed of 15 to 25 lobes.
They are arranged radially and are separated from one another by varying amounts of fat.
Each lobe consists of several lobules, which in turn are composed of numerous alveoli.
Each alveolus is provided with a small duct that joins others to form a single larger duct for each lobe .
These lactiferous ducts open separately on the nipple, where they may be distinguished as small but distinct orifices.
The alveolar secretory epithelium synthesizes the various milk constituents.
Figure 36-6.
Schematic of the alveolar and ductal system during lactation.
Note the myoepithelial fibers (M) that surround the outside of the uppermost alveolus.
The secretions from the glandular elements are extruded into the lumen of the alveoli (A) and ejected by the myoepithelial cells into the ductal system (D), which empties through the nipple.
Arterial blood supply to the alveolus is identified by the upper right arrow and venous drainage by the arrow beneath.
After delivery, the breasts begin to secrete colostrum, which is a deepyellow liquid.
It usually can be expressed from the nipples by the second postpartum day.
Compared with mature milk, colostrum is rich in immunological components and contains more minerals and amino acids .
It also has more protein, much of which is globulin, but less sugar and fat.
Secretion persists for 5 to 14 days, with gradual conversion to mature milk by 4 to 6 weeks.
The colostrum content of immunoglobulin A (IgA) offers the newborn protection against enteric pathogens.
Other host resistance factors found in colostrum and milk include complement, macrophages, lymphocytes, lactoferrin, lactoperoxidase, and lysozymes.
A lactating mother produces upwards of 600 mL of milk daily, and maternal gestational weight gain has little impact on its quantity or quality.
Mature milk is a complex and dynamic biological fluid that includes fat, proteins, carbohydrates, bioactive factors, minerals, vitamins, hormones, and many cellular products .
The contents and concentrations of human milk change even during a single feed and are influenced by maternal diet and by newborn age, health, and needs.
Milk is isotonic with plasma, and lactose accounts for half of the osmotic pressure.
Essential amino acids are derived from blood, and nonessential amino acids are derived in part from blood or synthesized in the mammary gland.
Most milk proteins are unique and include alpha-lactalbumin, beta-lactoglobulin, and casein.
Fatty acids are synthesized in the alveoli from glucose and are secreted by an apocrine-like process.
Variable amounts of most vitamins are found in human milk.
Vitamin K is virtually absent, and thus, an intramuscular dose is given to the newborn .
Vitamin D content is low, and newborn supplementation is recommended by the American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017).
Table 36-3.
Average Composition of Human Breast Milk Whey is milk serum and contains large amounts of interleukin-6 and other chemokines .
Human milk has a whey-to-casein ratio of 60:40, which is considered ideal for absorption.
Prolactin appears to be actively secreted into breast milk.
Epidermal growth factor has been identified, and because it is not destroyed by gastric proteolytic enzymes, it may be absorbed to promote growth and maturation of newborn intestinal mucosa.
Other critical components in human milk include melatonin and oligosaccharides.
# Lactation Endocrinology.
The precise humoral and neural mechanisms involved in lactation are complex.
Progesterone, estrogen, and placental lactogen, as well as prolactin,
cortisol, and insulin, appear to act in concert to stimulate the growth and development of the milk-secreting apparatus .
With delivery, the maternal serum levels of progesterone and estrogen decline abruptly and profoundly.
This drop removes the inhibitory influence of progesterone on alpha-lactalbumin production and stimulates lactose synthase to raise milk lactose levels.
Progesterone withdrawal also allows prolactin to act unopposed in its stimulation of alpha-lactalbumin production.
Activation of calcium-sensing receptors in mammary epithelial cells downregulates parathyroid hormone–related protein (PTHrP) and increases calcium transport into milk .
Serotonin also is produced in mammary epithelial cells and has a role in maintaining milk production .
The intensity and duration of subsequent lactation are controlled, in large part, by the repetitive stimulus of suckling and emptying of milk from the breast.
Prolactin is essential for lactation, and women with extensive pituitary necrosis—Sheehan syndrome—do not lactate .
Although plasma prolactin levels fall after delivery to levels lower than during pregnancy, each act of suckling triggers a rise in levels.
Presumably a stimulus from the breast curtails the release of dopamine—also known as prolactin-inhibiting factor—from the hypothalamus.
In turn, this transiently induces increased prolactin secretion.
The posterior pituitary secretes oxytocin in pulsatile fashion.
This stimulates milk expression from a lactating breast by causing contraction of myoepithelial cells in the alveoli and small milk ducts (see Fig. 36-6).
Milk ejection, or letting down, is a reflex initiated especially by suckling, which stimulates the posterior pituitary to liberate oxytocin.
The reflex may even be provoked by an infant cry and can be inhibited by maternal fright or stress .
# Immunological Consequences of Breastfeeding.
Human milk contains several protective immunological substances, including secretory IgA and growth factors.
The antibodies in human milk are specifically directed against maternal environmental antigens such as Escherichia coli .
According to the CDC, breastfeeding decreases the incidence of ear, respiratory, and gastrointestinal infections; necrotizing enterocolitis; and sudden infant death syndrome (SIDS) .
Breastfeeding is especially important for immunity in preterm infants .
Much attention has been directed to the role of maternal breast milk lymphocytes in neonatal immunological processes.
Milk contains both T and B lymphocytes, but the T lymphocytes appear to differ from those found in blood.
Specifically, milk T lymphocytes are almost exclusively composed of cells that exhibit specific membrane antigens.
These memory T cells appear to be an avenue for the neonate to benefit from the maternal immunological experience.
# Lactation.
The ideal time to begin breastfeeding is within an hour of birth.
Human milk is ideal food for newborns in that it provides age-specific nutrients, immunological factors, and antibacterial substances.
Milk also contains factors that act as biological signals for promoting cellular growth and differentiation.
A list of the advantages of breastfeeding is shown in Table 36-4.
Lactation has long-term benefits for both the mother and the infant.
For example, women who breastfeed have a lower risk of breast and reproductive cancer.
Children who were breastfed have higher adult intelligence scores independent of a wide range of possible confounding factors (Jong, 2012; Kramer, 2008).
In the short term, lactation is associated with less postpartum weight retention .
In addition, rates of SIDS are significantly lower among breast-fed infants.
Bartek and colleagues (2013) estimate that a 90-percent breastfeeding rate for 12 months would save more than $3 billion annually in excess infant and maternal morbidity costs.
For all these reasons, the American Academy of Pediatrics and American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) support the World Health Organization (2011) recommendations of exclusive breastfeeding for up to
6 months.
Table 36-4.
Advantages of Breastfeeding Currently, 55 percent of women breastfeed at 6 months compared with a Healthy People 2020 goal of 61 percent.
The Baby-Friendly Hospital Initiative is an international program to raise rates of exclusive breastfeeding and to extend its duration.
It is based on the World Health Organization (2018) Ten Steps to Successful Breastfeeding .
Worldwide, almost 20,000 hospitals are deemed “baby-friendly,” however, only 15 to 20 percent of hospitals in the United States are so designated (Baby-Friendly USA, 2018; Perrine, 2015).
In a large population-based study done in the United States, fewer than two thirds of term neonates were exclusively breastfed at the time of discharge .
By 3 months, according to the CDC, less than half of these infants are exclusively breastfed .
Table 36-5.
Ten Steps to Successful Breastfeeding Various individual resources are available online for lactating mothers from the American Academy of Pediatrics (www.aap.org) and La Leche League International (www.llli.org).
# Breast Care.
The nipples require little attention other than cleanliness and attention to skin fissures.
Fissured nipples render lactation painful, and they may have a deleterious influence on milk production.
These cracks also provide a portal of entry for pyogenic bacteria.
Because dried milk is likely to accumulate and irritate the nipples, washing the areola with water and mild soap is helpful before and after nursing.
When the nipples are irritated or fissured, some recommend topical lanolin and a nipple shield for 24 hours or longer .
If fissuring is severe, the newborn should not be permitted to nurse on the affected side.
Instead, the breast is emptied regularly with a pump until the lesions are healed.
Poor latching of the neonate to the breast can create such fissures.
For example, the newborn may take into its mouth only the nipple, which is then is forced against the hard palate during suckling.
Ideally, the nipple and areola are both taken in to evenly distribute suckling forces.
Moreover, the force of the hard palate against the lactiferous sinuses aids their efficient emptying, while the nipple is thereby positioned closer to the soft palate.
# Breastfeeding Contraindications.
Lactation is contraindicated in women who take street drugs or do not control their alcohol use; have an infant with galactosemia; have human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection; have active, untreated tuberculosis; take certain medications; or are undergoing breast cancer treatment .
Breastfeeding has been recognized for some time as a mode of HIV transmission and is proscribed in developed countries in which adequate nutrition is otherwise available .
Other viral infections do not contraindicate lactation.
For example, with maternal cytomegalovirus infection, both virus and antibodies are present in breast milk.
And, although hepatitis B virus is excreted in milk, breastfeeding is not contraindicated if hepatitis B immune globulin is given to the newborns of affected mothers.
Maternal hepatitis C infection is not a contraindication because breastfeeding has not been shown to transmit infection.
Women with active herpes simplex virus may suckle their infants if there are no breast lesions and if particular care is directed to hand washing before nursing.
From the CDC (2021a), those with COVID-19 should wear a mask and practice hand-hygiene.
# Drugs Secreted in Milk.
Most drugs given to the mother are secreted in breast milk, although the amount ingested by the infant typically is small.
Factors influencing drug excretion include plasma concentration, degree of protein binding, plasma and milk pH, degree of ionization, lipid solubility, and molecular weight .
The ratio of drug concentration in breast milk to that in maternal plasma is the milk-to-plasma drug-concentration ratio.
Ideally, to minimize infant exposure, medication selection favors drugs with a shorter half-life, poorer oral absorption, and lower lipid solubility.
If multiple daily drug doses are required, each is taken by the
mother after the closest feed.
Single daily-dosed drugs may be taken just before the longest infant sleep interval—usually at bedtime.
Only a few drugs are absolutely contraindicated while breastfeeding .
Cytotoxic drugs may interfere with cellular metabolism and potentially cause immune suppression or neutropenia, affect growth, and at least theoretically, increase the childhood cancer risk.
Examples include cyclophosphamide, cyclosporine, doxorubicin, methotrexate, and mycophenolate .
If a medication presents a concern, its importance should be ascertained.
A provider can also seek a safer alternative or determine if neonatal exposure can be minimized if the medication dose is taken immediately after each breastfeeding session.
Last, recreational drugs such as marijuana and alcohol should be avoided (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2017c; Metz, 2018).
Data on individual drugs are available through the National Institutes of Health website, LactMed, which can be found at www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK501922/.
Radioactive isotopes of copper, gallium, indium, iodine, sodium, and technetium rapidly appear in breast milk.
Consultation with a nuclear medicine specialist is recommended before performing a diagnostic study with these isotopes .
Ideally, a radionuclide with the shortest excretion time in breast milk is selected.
The mother should pump her breasts before the study and store enough milk in a freezer to feed the infant.
After the study, she should pump her breasts to maintain milk production but discard all milk produced during the time that radioactivity is present.
This ranges from 15 hours to 2 weeks, depending on the isotope used.
Importantly, radioactive iodine concentrates and persists in the thyroid.
Its special considerations are discussed in Chapter 66 (p. 1174).
For magnetic resonance (MR) imaging, breastfeeding should not be interrupted after gadolinium administration .
# Breast Engorgement.
This is common in women who do not breastfeed.
It is typified by milk leakage and breast pain, which peak 3 to 5 days after delivery.
Up to half of affected women require analgesia for breast pain relief, and as many as 10 percent report severe pain for up to 14 days.
Evidence is insufficient to firmly support any specific treatment .
That said, breasts can be supported with a well-fitting brassiere, breast binder, or sports bra.
Cool packs and oral analgesics for 12 to 24 hours aid discomfort.
Pharmacological or hormonal agents in general are not recommended to suppress lactation.
Fever caused by breast engorgement was common before the renaissance of breastfeeding.
In one study, 13 percent of puerperas with engorgement had fever ranging from 37.8 to 39°C .
Fever seldom persists for longer than 4 to 16 hours.
The incidence and severity of engorgement and of the fever associated with it are much lower if women breastfeed.
Other causes of fever, especially those due to infection, must be excluded.
Mastitis is infection of the mammary parenchyma and is relatively common in lactating women .
# Other Lactation Issues.
With inverted nipples, lactiferous ducts open directly into a depression at the center of the areola.
With these depressed nipples, nursing is difficult.
If the depression is not deep, milk sometimes can be drawn out by a breast pump.
If instead the nipple is greatly inverted, daily attempts are made during the last few months of pregnancy to draw or “tease” the nipple out with the fingers.
Extra breasts—polymastia, or extra nipples—polythelia, may develop along the former embryonic mammary ridge.
Also termed the milk line, this line extends from the axilla to the groin bilaterally.
In some women, rests of accessory breast tissue can be found in the mons pubis or vulva .
In the general population, the incidence of accessory breast tissue ranges from 0.22 to 6 percent .
These breasts may be so small as to be mistaken for pigmented moles, or if without a nipple, for lymphadenopathy or lipoma.
Polymastia has no obstetrical significance, although occasionally enlargement of
these accessory breasts during pregnancy or engorgement postpartum may result in patient discomfort and anxiety.
Galactocele is a milk duct that becomes obstructed by inspissated secretions.
The amount is ordinarily limited, but an excess may form a fluctuant mass—a galactocele—that can cause pressure symptoms and have the appearance of an abscess.
It may resolve spontaneously or require aspiration.
Among individuals, the volume of milk secreted varies markedly.
This depends not on general maternal health but on breast glandular development.
Rarely, there is complete lack of mammary secretion—agalactia.
Occasionally, mammary secretion is excessive—polygalactia.
Lactation-Associated Osteoporosis This is a rare disorder of unknown etiology that may be associated with severe back pain or vertebral fractures (Li, 2018; Zhang, 2017).
Preliminary studies indicate that bisphosphonates are effective in its management.
However, for almost all women, lactation is not associated with later-onset osteoporosis .
Pregnancy-associated osteoporosis is discussed in Chapter 61 (p. 1100).
Hospital Care.
For 2 hours after delivery, blood pressure and pulse are taken every 15 minutes, at minimum.
Temperature is assessed every 4 hours for the first 8 hours and then at least every 8 hours subsequently .
If regional analgesia or general anesthesia was used for labor or delivery, the mother should be observed in an appropriately equipped and staffed recovery area.
Expected anesthesia recovery and complications are described in Chapter 25 (p. 473).
Because the likelihood of significant hemorrhage is greatest immediately postpartum, vaginal bleeding is closely monitored.
The uterine fundus is palpated to ensure that it is well contracted.
If relaxation is detected, the uterus should be massaged through the abdominal wall until it remains contracted.
Uterotonics also are sometimes required.
Blood may accumulate within the uterus without external bleeding.
This may be detected early by uterine enlargement during fundal palpation in the first postdelivery hours.
Postpartum hemorrhage is discussed in Chapter 41.
Early ambulation within a few hours after delivery is encouraged.
An attendant should be present for at least the first time, in case the woman becomes syncopal.
The many confirmed advantages of early ambulation include fewer bladder complications, less frequent constipation, and reduced rates of puerperal venous thromboembolism.
As discussed, deep-vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism are common in the puerperium.
In our audits of puerperal women at Parkland Hospital, the frequency of venous thromboembolism is extremely low.
We attribute this to early ambulation.
Risk factors and other measures to diminish the frequency of thromboembolism are discussed in Chapter 55 (p. 984).
Diets need not be restricted for women who give birth vaginally.
Generally, two hours after uncomplicated vaginal delivery, a woman is allowed to eat.
With lactation, the level of calories and protein consumed during pregnancy is increased slightly as recommended by the Food and Nutrition Board of the National Research Council .
If the mother does not breastfeed, dietary requirements are the same as for a nonpregnant woman.
We recommend oral iron supplementation for at least 3 months after delivery and hematocrit evaluation at the first postpartum visit.
As noted earlier, profound drops in estrogen levels follow removal of the placenta.
Reminiscent of the menopause, postpartum women may experience hot flushes, especially at night.
Importantly, the patient’s temperature is assessed to differentiate these physiological vasomotor events from infection.
In women with migraines, dramatic hypoestrogenism may trigger headaches.
Importantly, severe headaches should be differentiated from postdural puncture headache or hypertensive complications.
Care varies depending on headache severity.
Mild headaches may respond to analgesics such as ibuprofen or acetaminophen.
For more severe headaches, oral or systemic narcotics can be used.
Alternatively, a triptan, such as
sumatriptan (Imitrex), can relieve headaches by causing intracranial vasoconstriction, and it is breastfeeding compatible.
# Perineal Care.
The woman is instructed to clean the vulva from anterior to posterior—the vulva toward the anus.
A cool pack applied to the perineum may help reduce edema and discomfort during the first 24 hours if there is a perineal laceration or an episiotomy.
Most women also appear to obtain a measure of relief from the periodic application of a local anesthetic spray.
Severe perineal, vaginal, or rectal pain always warrants careful inspection and palpation.
Severe discomfort usually indicates a problem, such as a hematoma within the first day or so and infection after the third or fourth day (Chap. 37, p. 657 and Chap. 42, p. 740).
Beginning approximately 24 hours after delivery, moist heat as provided by warm sitz baths can reduce local discomfort.
Tub bathing after uncomplicated delivery is allowed.
The episiotomy incision normally is firmly healed and nearly asymptomatic by the third week.
Rarely, the cervix, and occasionally a portion of the uterine body, may protrude from the vulva following delivery.
This is accompanied by variable degrees of anterior and posterior vaginal wall prolapse.
Symptoms include a palpable mass at or past the introitus, voiding difficulties, or pressure.
Puerperal procidentia typically improves with time as the weight of the uterus lessens with involution.
As a temporizing measure for pronounced prolapse, the uterus can be replaced and held in position with a space-filling pessary, such as a donut type.
Rectal veins are often congested at term.
Thrombosis of these hemorrhoids is common and may be promoted by second-stage pushing.
Treatment includes topically applied anesthetics, warm soaks, and stoolsoftening agents.
Nonprescription topical preparations containing corticosteroids, astringents, or phenylephrine are often used.
However, no randomized studies support their efficacy compared with symptomatic care.
# Bladder Function.
In most delivery units, intravenous fluids are infused during labor and for an hour or so after vaginal delivery.
Oxytocin, in doses that have an antidiuretic effect, is typically infused postpartum, and rapid bladder filling is common.
Moreover, both bladder sensation and capability to empty spontaneously may be diminished by components of the labor and delivery process.
Thus, urinary retention and bladder overdistention is common in the early puerperium.
The incidence in more than 5500 women studied with a bladder scanner was 5 percent .
It is much less clinically.
Risk factors that increased the likelihood of retention include primiparity, epidural analgesia, cesarean delivery, perineal lacerations, operative vaginal delivery, catheterization during labor, and prolonged second-stage labor (Stephansson, 2016; Wang, 2017).
Prevention of bladder overdistention demands observation after delivery to ensure that the bladder does not overfill and that it empties adequately with each voiding.
The enlarged bladder can be palpated suprapubically, or it is evident abdominally indirectly as it elevates the fundus above the umbilicus.
Most currently use an automated sonography system to detect high bladder volumes and thus postpartum urinary retention .
If a woman has not voided within 4 hours after delivery, it is likely that she cannot.
If she has trouble voiding initially, she also is likely to have further trouble.
First, an examination for perineal and genital-tract hematomas is completed, as these may be contributory.
With an overdistended bladder, an indwelling catheter should be placed and left until the factors causing retention have abated.
Even without a demonstrable cause, it usually is best to leave the catheter in place for at least 24 hours.
This prevents recurrence and allows recovery of normal bladder tone and sensation.
When the catheter is removed, a voiding trial is completed to demonstrate an ability to void appropriately.
If a woman cannot void after 4 hours, urine volumes are measured sonographically.
If more than 200
mL, the bladder is not functioning appropriately, and the catheter is replaced and remains for another 24 hours.
Although rare, if retention persists after a second voiding trial, an indwelling catheter and leg bag can be elected, and the patient returns in 1 week for an outpatient voiding trial.
In a study of 27 women with a protracted course, all resumed normal voiding by 3 weeks postpartum .
During a voiding trial, if less than 200 mL of urine is obtained, the catheter can be removed and the bladder subsequently monitored clinically and sonographically as described earlier.
Harris and coworkers (1977) reported that 40 percent of such women develop bacteriuria, and thus a single dose or short course of antimicrobial therapy against uropathogens is reasonable after the catheter is removed.
# Pain, Mood, and Cognition.
Discomfort and its causes following cesarean delivery are considered in Chapter 30 (p. 565).
During the first few days after vaginal delivery, the mother may be uncomfortable because of afterpains, episiotomy and lacerations, breast engorgement, and at times, postdural puncture headache.
Mild analgesics containing codeine, ibuprofen, or acetaminophen, preferably in combinations, are given as frequently as every 4 hours during the first few days.
It is important to screen the postpartum woman for depression .
Commonly, mothers exhibit some degree of depressed mood a few days after delivery.
Termed postpartum blues, this likely is the consequence of several factors.
These include the emotional letdown that follows the excitement and fears experienced during pregnancy and delivery, discomforts of the early puerperium, fatigue from sleep deprivation, anxiety over the ability to provide appropriate newborn care, and body image concerns.
In most women, effective treatment includes anticipation, recognition, and reassurance.
This disorder is usually mild and self-limited to 2 to 3 days, although it sometimes lasts for up to 10 days.
Should these moods persist or worsen, an evaluation for symptoms of major depression is done .
Last, postpartum hormonal changes in some women may affect brain function.
Bannbers and colleagues (2013) observed a functional decline in executive function in postpartum women.
# Neuromusculoskeletal Problems.
Obstetrical Neuropathies Pressure on branches of the lumbosacral nerve plexus during labor may manifest as complaints of intense neuralgia or cramplike pains extending down one or both legs as soon as the head descends into the pelvis.
If the nerve is injured, pain may continue after delivery, and variable degrees of sensory loss or muscle paralysis can result.
In some cases, there is footdrop, which can be secondary to injury at the level of the lumbosacral plexus, sciatic nerve, or common fibular (peroneal) nerve .
Components of the lumbosacral plexus cross the pelvic brim and can be compressed by the fetal head or by forceps.
The common fibular nerves may be externally compressed when the legs are positioned in stirrups, especially during prolonged second-stage labor.
Obstetrical neuropathy is relatively infrequent.
Evaluation of more than 6000 puerperas found that approximately 1 percent had a confirmed nerve injury .
Lateral femoral cutaneous neuropathies were the most common (24 percent), followed by femoral neuropathies (14 percent).
A motor deficit accompanied a third of injuries.
Nulliparity, prolonged secondstage labor, and pushing for a long duration in the semi-Fowler position were risk factors.
The median duration of symptoms was 2 months, and the range was 2 weeks to 18 months.
Injury of the iliohypogastric and ilioinguinal nerves may occur with cesarean delivery (Rahn, 2010; Yazici Yilmaz, 2018).
We have rarely encountered lumbar arachnoiditis following epidural analgesia causing severe bilateral neuropathic pain.
Musculoskeletal Injuries Pain in the pelvic girdle, hips, or lower extremities may follow stretching or tearing injuries sustained at normal or difficult delivery.
MR imaging is often informative when clinical examination is normal .
Most injuries resolve
with antiinflammatory agents and physical therapy.
Rarely, there may be septic pyomyositis such as with iliopsoas muscle abscess (Nelson, 2010; Young, 2010).
Separation of the symphysis pubis or one of the sacroiliac synchondroses during labor leads to pain and marked interference with locomotion (Fig. 36- 7).
Estimates of the frequency of this event vary widely from 1 in 600 to 1 in 30,000 deliveries (Reis, 1932; Taylor, 1986).
In our experiences, symptomatic separations are uncommon.
Their onset of pain is often acute during delivery, but symptoms may manifest either antepartum or up to 48 hours postpartum .
Radiography is typically used for evaluation.
The normal distance of the symphyseal joint is 0.4 to 0.5 cm, and symphyseal separation >1 cm is diagnostic for diastasis.
Treatment is generally conservative, with rest in a lateral decubitus position and an appropriately fitted pelvic binder .
Surgery is occasionally necessary in some symphyseal separations >4 cm .
The recurrence risk is high in subsequent pregnancies, and Culligan and associates (2002) recommend consideration for cesarean delivery.
Figure 36-7.
Pubic symphyseal separation found on the first postpartum day following vaginal delivery of a 2840-g newborn.
The patient had pain over the pubic bone and pain with ambulation.
A shuffling gait was noted, and she had difficulty with leg elevation when supine.
The patient was treated with physical therapy and analgesics.
A pelvic binder was applied, and a rolling walker was provided.
She improved quickly and was discharged home on postpartum day 5.
In rare cases, fractures of the sacrum or pubic ramus are caused by even uncomplicated deliveries (Alonso-Burgos, 2007; Speziali, 2015).
Discussed in Chapter 61 (p. 1100), the latter is more likely with osteoporosis associated with heparin or corticosteroid therapy.
In rare but serious cases, bacterial osteomyelitis—osteitis pubis—can be devastating.
Lawford and coworkers (2010) reported such a case that caused massive vulvar edema.
# Immunizations.
The D-negative woman who is not isoimmunized and whose newborn is Dpositive is given 300 μg of anti-D immune globulin shortly after delivery .
Women who are not already immune to rubella or varicella are excellent candidates for vaccination before discharge .
Those who have not received a tetanus/diphtheria (Tdap/Td) or influenza vaccine should be given these (Table 10-7, p. 189).
The CDC (2021b) recommends the COVID-19 vaccine, and includes breastfeeding women.
Morgan and colleagues (2015) reported that implementation of a bestpractices alert in the electronic medical record was associated with a Tdap immunization rate of 97 percent at Parkland Hospital.
When permissible by law, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019) recommends standing orders for indicated immunizations.
# Contraception.
During the hospital stay, a concerted effort is made to provide family planning education.
Various forms of contraception are discussed throughout Chapter 38 and sterilization procedures in Chapter 39.
The immediate puerperium is an ideal time for consideration of long-acting reversible contraception—LARC .
Women not breastfeeding have return of menses usually within 6 to 8 weeks.
At times, however, it is difficult clinically to assign a specific date to the first menstrual period after delivery.
A minority of women bleed small to moderate amounts intermittently starting soon after delivery.
Ovulation occurs at a mean of 7 weeks but ranges from 5 to 11 weeks .
That said, ovulation before 28 days has been described .
Thus, conception is possible during the early puerperium.
Women who become sexually active during the puerperium and who do not desire to conceive should initiate contraception.
Kelly and associates (2005) reported that by the third month postpartum, 58 percent of adolescents had resumed sexual intercourse, but only 80 percent of these were using contraception.
Because of this, many recommend LARC during the puerperium.
Women who breastfeed ovulate much less frequently compared with
those who do not, but variation is great.
Timing of ovulation depends on individual biological variation and the intensity of breastfeeding.
Lactating women may first menstruate as early as the second or as late as the 18th month after delivery.
Campbell and Gray (1993) analyzed daily urine specimens in 92 lactating women.
Breastfeeding in general delays resumption of ovulation, although it does not invariably forestall it.
Other findings in their study included the following: 1. Resumption of ovulation was frequently marked by return of normal menstrual bleeding.
2. Breastfeeding episodes lasting 15 minutes seven times daily delayed ovulation resumption.
3. Ovulation can occur without bleeding.
4. Bleeding can be anovulatory.
5. The risk of pregnancy in breastfeeding women was approximately 4 percent per year.
For the breastfeeding woman, progestin-only contraceptives, such as progestin pills, depot medroxyprogesterone, or progestin implants or IUDs, do not affect the quality or quantity of milk.
Not available in the United States, success with the progesterone-releasing vaginal ring also has been described .
These may be initiated any time during the puerperium.
Estrogen-progestin contraceptives likely reduce the quantity of breast milk, but under the proper circumstances, they too can be used by lactating women.
These hormonal methods are discussed in Chapter 38 (p. 671).
# Hospital Discharge.
Following uncomplicated vaginal delivery, hospitalization is seldom warranted for more than 48 hours.
Hospital stay length following labor and delivery is now regulated by federal law .
Currently, the norms are hospital stays up to 48 hours following uncomplicated vaginal delivery and up to 96 hours following uncomplicated cesarean delivery (American Academy of Pediatrics and American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2017; Blumenfield, 2015).
Earlier hospital discharge is acceptable for appropriately selected women if they desire it.
A woman should receive instructions concerning anticipated normal physiological puerperal changes, including lochia patterns, weight loss from diuresis, and milk let-down.
She also should receive instructions concerning fever, excessive vaginal bleeding, or leg pain, swelling, or tenderness.
Persistent headaches, shortness of breath, or chest pain warrant immediate concern.
Home Care.
# Coitus.
No evidence-based data guide resumption of coitus after delivery, and practices are individualized .
After 2 weeks, coitus may be resumed based on desire and comfort.
Wallwiener and colleagues (2017) reported that 60 percent of women resumed sexual activity by 1 week and 80 percent by 4 months.
They also reported that a third of these women had sexual dysfunction.
Intercourse too soon may be unpleasant, if not painful, and this may be related to episiotomy incisions or perineal lacerations.
In a study of women without an episiotomy, only 0.4 percent of those with a first- or seconddegree tear had dyspareunia .
Conversely, in primiparas with an episiotomy, 67 percent had sexual dysfunction at 3 months, 31 percent at 6 months, and 15 percent at 12 months .
Only 40 percent of women with an anal sphincter injury had resumed intercourse by 12 weeks .
Last, dyspareunia was also common following cesarean delivery .
Postpartum, the vulvovaginal epithelium is thin, and very little lubrication follows sexual stimulation.
This stems from the hypoestrogenic state following delivery, which lasts until ovulation resumes.
It may be particularly problematic in breastfeeding women who are hypoestrogenic for many months postpartum .
For treatment, small amounts of topical estrogen cream can be applied daily for several weeks to vulvar tissues.
Additionally, vaginal lubricants may be used with coitus.
This same thinning of the vulvovaginal epithelium can lead to dysuria.
Topical estrogen can again be offered once cystitis is excluded.
# Follow-Up Care.
By discharge, women who had an uncomplicated vaginal delivery can resume most activities, including bathing, driving, and household functions.
Despite this, Tulman
and Fawcett (1988) reported that only half of mothers regained their usual level of energy by 6 weeks.
Women who delivered vaginally were twice as likely to have normal energy levels at this time compared with those with a cesarean delivery.
Ideally, the care and nurturing of the infant should be provided by the mother with ample help from the father.
Jimenez and Newton (1979) tabulated cross-cultural information on 202 societies from various international geographical regions.
Following childbirth, most societies did not restrict work activity, and approximately half expected a return to full duties within 2 weeks.
Wallace and coworkers (2013) reported that 80 percent of women who worked during pregnancy resume work by 1 year after delivery.
Discussed on page 634, during this fourth trimester, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018a) recommends a comprehensive visit within 12 weeks after delivery.
This has proved quite satisfactory to identify abnormalities beyond the immediate puerperium and to initiate contraceptive practices.